<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RDS Performance Insights &amp; Query Optimization</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on RDS Performance Insights &amp; Query Optimization</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/query-optimization/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/query-optimization/overview/</guid>
      <description>Query Optimization Overview 🎯 What is Query Optimization? Query optimization is the process of improving database query performance through various techniques including index optimization, query rewriting, and execution plan analysis.&#xA;Info: Effective query optimization can improve performance by 70% or more while reducing resource consumption.&#xA;🚀 Optimization Techniques 1. Index Optimization Composite Indexes: Multi-column indexes for complex queries Partial Indexes: Indexes with WHERE conditions Covering Indexes: Include all needed columns Index Maintenance: Regular monitoring and cleanup 2.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prerequisites &amp; Requirements</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/preparation/prerequisites/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/preparation/prerequisites/</guid>
      <description>Prerequisites &amp;amp; Requirements 🔧 Technical Prerequisites AWS Account Requirements AWS Account: Active AWS account with appropriate permissions RDS Access: Ability to modify RDS instances and parameter groups IAM Permissions: Required permissions for Performance Insights and CloudWatch Billing Access: Understanding of potential costs for extended retention Supported Database Engines Performance Insights is available for:&#xA;Engine Minimum Version Notes Amazon Aurora MySQL 5.6.10a Full feature support Amazon Aurora PostgreSQL 9.6.3 Full feature support RDS for MySQL 5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is RDS Performance Insights?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/introduction/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/introduction/overview/</guid>
      <description>What is RDS Performance Insights? 📊 Overview Amazon RDS Performance Insights is a database performance tuning and monitoring feature that helps you quickly assess the load on your database and determine when and where to take action. It provides a comprehensive view of your database performance, making it easier to identify bottlenecks and optimize query performance.&#xA;Info Performance Insights is available for Amazon Aurora, RDS for MySQL, MariaDB, PostgreSQL, Oracle, and SQL Server.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benefits &amp; ROI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/introduction/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/introduction/benefits/</guid>
      <description>Benefits &amp;amp; Return on Investment 💰 Financial Impact Cost Savings Breakdown Category Annual Savings Percentage Infrastructure Optimization $350,000 54% Operational Efficiency $200,000 31% Reduced Downtime $100,000 15% Total Annual Savings $650,000 100% ROI Calculation Initial Investment: $260,000 (implementation + training) Annual Savings: $650,000 ROI: 250% in 18 months Break-even Point: 6.2 months 📊 Performance Improvements Before vs After Implementation Metric Before After Improvement Average Query Response Time 3-5 seconds 1-1.5 seconds 70% Database Availability 97.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environment Setup</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/preparation/environment-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 11:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/preparation/environment-setup/</guid>
      <description>Environment Setup 🏗️ Development Environment Local Development Setup Required Tools Installation # Install AWS CLI curl &amp;#34;https://awscli.amazonaws.com/awscli-exe-linux-x86_64.zip&amp;#34; -o &amp;#34;awscliv2.zip&amp;#34; unzip awscliv2.zip sudo ./aws/install # Verify installation aws --version # Configure AWS credentials aws configure Database Client Tools # PostgreSQL client sudo apt-get install postgresql-client # MySQL client sudo apt-get install mysql-client # Universal database client (optional) sudo snap install dbeaver-ce Monitoring Tools # Install Python for custom scripts sudo apt-get install python3 python3-pip # Install required Python packages pip3 install boto3 pandas matplotlib psycopg2-binary pymysql 🔧 AWS Environment Configuration IAM Setup Create Performance Insights Role # Create IAM policy for Performance Insights aws iam create-policy \ --policy-name PerformanceInsightsPolicy \ --policy-document file://performance-insights-policy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Insights Overview</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/overview/</guid>
      <description>What is Performance Insights? Amazon RDS Performance Insights is a database performance monitoring tool that helps you:&#xA;Analyze database performance visually and intuitively Identify bottlenecks and performance issues Optimize queries based on real data Monitor real-time and historical performance Key Features 1. Database Load Monitoring DB Load: Average number of active sessions Wait Events: Database wait events Top SQL: Most resource-intensive queries 2. Visual Dashboard Timeline view: View performance over time Top dimensions: Analyze by user, host, database Drill-down capability: Deep dive into specific metrics 3.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Setting up RDS Instance with Performance Insights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/setup/</guid>
      <description>1. Creating RDS Instance with Performance Insights Step 1: Access RDS Console Log in to AWS Console Search for &amp;ldquo;RDS&amp;rdquo; in the search bar Click on &amp;ldquo;Amazon RDS&amp;rdquo; Step 2: Create Database Click the orange &amp;ldquo;Create database&amp;rdquo; button Select &amp;ldquo;Standard create&amp;rdquo; (not Easy create) Engine options: • Choose MySQL (or PostgreSQL as needed) • Version: Select the latest version (e.g., MySQL 8.0.35) Step 3: Templates and Settings Templates: Choose &amp;ldquo;Free tier&amp;rdquo; (if eligible) or &amp;ldquo;Dev/Test&amp;rdquo; Settings: • DB instance identifier: mydb-performance-test • Master username: admin • Master password: Create a strong password or select &amp;ldquo;Auto generate&amp;rdquo; Step 4: Instance Configuration DB instance class: • Select &amp;ldquo;Burstable classes (includes t classes)&amp;rdquo; • Choose db.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Performance Insights Dashboard</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/dashboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/dashboard/</guid>
      <description>Dashboard Overview The Performance Insights dashboard provides a comprehensive view of your database performance with several key sections:&#xA;1. Database Load Chart The main chart shows database load over time, measured in Average Active Sessions (AAS).&#xA;Key Elements:&#xA;Y-axis: Database load (AAS) X-axis: Time Horizontal line: vCPU count (performance baseline) Colored areas: Different wait event types 2. Top Dimensions Panel Shows the top contributors to database load by various dimensions:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query Optimization with Performance Insights</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/performance-insights/optimization/</guid>
      <description>Query Optimization Process Using Performance Insights for query optimization follows a systematic approach:&#xA;Identify problematic queries using Top SQL Analyze query execution patterns and wait events Investigate query execution plans Apply optimization techniques Monitor optimization results Identifying Problematic Queries Using Top SQL Panel The Top SQL panel shows queries ranked by their contribution to database load:&#xA;Top SQL (by Load) ┌─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐ │ SQL ID: 0x1A2B3C4D5E6F | Load: 3.2 AAS (40%) │ │ SELECT * FROM orders WHERE order_date &amp;gt; ?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Usage Examples in Hugo</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/image-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/image-examples/</guid>
      <description>Examples of Adding Images 1. Basic Image ![Image description](/images/image-name.jpg) Result: 2. Image with Custom Size &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/images/image-name.jpg&amp;#34; alt=&amp;#34;Description&amp;#34; width=&amp;#34;600&amp;#34; height=&amp;#34;400&amp;#34;&amp;gt; Result: 3. Image with Caption ![RDS Performance](/images/rds-performance.png) *Figure 1: RDS Performance Dashboard* Result: Figure 1: RDS Performance Dashboard&#xA;4. Multiple Images in One Section Step 1: Create Dashboard Step 2: Add Widget Step 3: Configure Metric 5. Image with Link [![Click to view full size](/images/thumbnail.png)](/images/full-size.png) 6. Image with Border and Center Alignment &amp;lt;div align=&amp;#34;center&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/images/architecture-diagram.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
